{"tossups": [{"question": "<em>Baseball player Willie Horton tried to save lives in this city</em>. Three murders in this city were the subject of John Hersey's book <em>The Algiers Motel Incident</em>. John Conyers went through this city with a bullhorn trying to calm people.After the police raided a bar called a \"blind pig\" on 12th Street, a disturbance began in this city which forced Governor George Romney to call in the National Guard. For 10 points, name this Michigan city, the site of a massive 1967 riot.", "answer": "<b><u>Detroit</u></b>, Michigan  {I}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>Followers of this belief system included Ulfilas, who invented an alphabet for the Gothic</em> <em>language to teach it to the Goths.</em> This belief was censured after the Greek word \"homoousios\" was used in a new statement of doctrine. Athanasius of Alexandria opposed the namesake of this system, who taught that Jesus was not coequal with God the Father because the Son was created later. For 10 points, name this eponymous heresy condemned in 313 at the Council of Nicaea.", "answer": "<b><u>Arian</u></b>ism [or <b><u>Arian</u></b> heresy; or <b><u>Arian</u></b> Christianity; prompt on<b><u> Christianity</u></b>; prompt on <b><u>anti-trinitarianism</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em>A rebellion against this world leader's country featured insurgents scaling Mount Tantalus</em>. In his highest office, this man sent lobbyist Lorrin Thurston to Washington, pardoned the revolutionary Robert William Wilcox, and was initially condemned by the findings of the Blount Report. This man became president after an 1893 coup overthrew Queen Liliuokalani. For 10 points, name this cousin of a pineapple magnate who served as the President of Hawaii.", "answer": "Sanford <b><u>Dole</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>Late in life, this man created the first church in Brattahlid.</em> After converting to Christianity, this man was sent by King Olaf Tryggvason to spread the faith to Greenland. One of his subordinates, Tyrker, went missing due to his discovery of grapes. This son of Erik the Red may have created the L'Anse aux Meadows (<b>pr. LANS-oh Meadows</b>) site as a settlement in what he called Vinland. For 10 points, name this Viking, the first European to make landfall in North America.", "answer": "Leif <b><u>Ericson</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>The reporter Nellie Bly took that name as a reference to this man</em>. This man died after gouging his head on a washbasin in a Bowery hotel. He honored his wife Jane by writing a piece that begins with the speaker \"dreaming of Jeanie with the light brown hair.\" This man wrote a song that begins \"way down upon da Swanee River,\" which is the state song of Florida. For 10 points, name this man who wrote such \"minstrel\" songs as \"Camptown Races\" and \"Oh! Susanna.\"", "answer": "Stephen <b><u>Foster</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>This event may have been inspired by the similar actions of Bernadino di Siena decades</em> <em>earlier.</em> This event was opposed by the \"Mad Dogs\" and supported by the \"Weepers.\" This event centered on a large wooden pyramid in the Piazza del Signoria. Targets of this event included Botticelli's myth-inspired artwork, the <em>Decameron</em>, playing cards, and wigs. For 10 points, name this event in which followers of Savonarola burned sinful objects.", "answer": "<b><u>Bonfire</u></b> of the <b><u>Vanitie</u></b>s", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em>Li Ling was a general who served this dynasty.</em> The founder of this dynasty fought against Xiang (<b>pr. SHEE-ang</b>) Yu of the Chu, winning the Battle of Gaixia (<b>pr. GAI-shee-uh</b>). During this dynasty, founded by Liu Bang, Sima Qian (pr. CHAN) wrote the Records of the Grand Historian. This dynasty came to an end when the Yellow Turban rebellion kicked off the Three Kingdoms Period. For 10 points, name this Chinese dynasty once ruled by Emperor Wu, which gives its name to the main Chinese ethnic group.", "answer": "<b><u>Han</u></b> dynasty  {I}", "metadata": "JZ"}, {"question": "<em>When this film won an Oscar, its screenwriter shouted \"The British are coming!\"</em> This movie's title comes from the William Blake poem \"Jerusalem.\" In it, Harold Abrahams overcomes anti-Semitism, while Eric Liddell refuses to compete on Sundays. This film is best known for the Vangelis composed instrumental theme, which plays over slow motion scenes of people running on a beach. For 10 points, name this 1981 British film about Olympic runners.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Chariots of Fire</u></b></em>  {I}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>After leaving office, this leader admitted responsibility for his party\u2019s \u201cblack money affair.\u201d</em>This man defeated Oscar LaFontaine, the Minister-President of Saarland, in one election, and a newly constructed executive building was nicknamed for this man. This close ally of Francois Mitterrand was a chief architect of the Maastricht Treaty creating the EU and was the longest chairman of the Christian Democratic Union, serving during the Berlin Wall\u2019s fall. For 10 points, name this first chancellor of a reunited Germany.", "answer": "Helmut <b><u>Kohl</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "AG"}, {"question": "<em>This location was recaptured after Arthur Saint Clair placed cannons on Sugar Hill.</em> The building of this structure was countered by the building of Fort William Henry, on the opposite side of Lake George. This structure was originally built by Michel de Lotbini\u00e8re, and was called Fort Carillon. During the siege of Boston, Henry Knox used cannons brought from this location. For 10 points, name this fort captured by Ethan Allen.", "answer": "Fort <b><u>Ticonderoga</u></b> [accept Fort <b><u>Carillon</u></b> before mentioned]  {I}", "metadata": "SH"}, {"question": "<em>One of this author\u2019s historical novels is divided into sections such as \u201cRecalled to Life\u201d and</em> <em>\u201cThe Golden Thread.\u201d</em> This author wrote a historical novel featuring a raven named Grip which is set during the Gordon Riots<em>.</em> This author of <em>Barnaby Rudge</em> used the line \u201cit is a far, far, better thing that I do, than I have ever done\u201d to end his novel in which Sidney Carton trades his life to save Charles Darnay. For 10 points, name this author of <em>A Tale of Two Cities</em>.", "answer": "Charles <b><u>Dickens</u> </b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "<em>The Smithsonian was established during this person\u2019s Presidency, and he was helped by</em> <em>James Birney in an election.</em> This person lowered the Black Tariff by passing the Walker Tariff. He defeated Lewis Cass to obtain his party\u2019s nomination and negotiated with Lord Aberdeen to obtain a boundary at the 49th Parallel for Oregon. Texas became a state following his election as President. For 10 points, name this successor of John Tyler who won the Election of 1844.", "answer": "James Knox <b><u>Polk</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This man argued with Ursus over who first invented</em> <em>prosthaphaeresis.</em> This scientist built the castle Uraniborg after being gifted the island of Hven. This man proposed a model for the Solar System that combined both geocentric and heliocentric ideas. In a duel over mathematics, this man lost part of his nose. One of this astronomer's students was Johannes Kepler. For 10 points, many stellar observations were made in the sixteenth century by what Danish astronomer?", "answer": "Tycho <b><u>Brahe</u></b> [or Tyge Otteson <b><u>Brahe</u></b>]", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This event was precipitated by Operation Anadyr, and the only combat fatality in this event</em> <em>was Rudolf Anderson</em>. U Thant helped negotiate an end to this event. During this event, Valerian Zorin was confronted by Adlai Stevenson in a UN Security Council meeting, and it was triggered by photographs taken by a U-2. It resulted in the creation of a Hotline. For 10 points, name this Cold War standoff over weapons placed by the USSR in the namesake Caribbean island.", "answer": "<b><u>Cuban Missile</u></b> Crisis [or <b><u>October</u></b> crisis; accept <b><u>Caribbean</u></b> crisis until Caribbean]  In return for the removal of missiles from Cuba, the U.S. pledged to remove Jupiter missiles from Italy and what Middle Eastern nation where they faced Russia?  ANSWER: <b><u>Turkey</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "JZ"}, {"question": "<em>A list of grievances against this king was collected in the Grand Remonstrance.</em> A part of this king's reign was dubbed the \"Eleven Years' Tyranny.\" This king controversially married Henrietta Maria and appointed William Laud as Archbishop of Canterbury. This king's nephew, Prince Rupert of the Rhine, unsuccessfully led his army at Marston Moor and Naseby. For 10 points, name this king who lost the English Civil War to Oliver Cromwell and was beheaded in 1649.", "answer": "<b><u>Charles I</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>Members of this group marched fully armed into the California state legislature to protest the</em> <em>gun control legislation in the Mulford Act</em>. This group originated in West Oakland and instituted a free breakfast for children program in several major cities. The FBI heavily targeted this group, which was co-founded by Bobby Seale. For 10 points, name this radical African-American political group whose members included H. Rap Brown and Eldridge Cleaver.", "answer": "<b><u>Black Panther</u></b>s [or <b><u>Black Panther</u></b> Party for Self Defense]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This battle followed the Siege of Famagusta.</em> In this battle,Agostino Barbarigo was killed while leading the left wing of the winning side. Uluc Ali fled from this battle carrying the flag of Malta, and galleasses were used effectively by the winners of this battle, who included Andrea Doria. Miguel de Cervantes lost an arm in this battle, where Ali Pasha was killed. For 10 points, name this naval battle where the Holy League defeated the Ottoman Empire in 1571.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Lepanto</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This ruler's army defeated the Bar Confederation.</em> This ruler formulated a law code known as the Nakaz. In response to the American Revolution, this ruler pushed for the formation of the League of Armed Neutrality. A subordinate of this ruler supposedly built fake villages in the Crimea. This ruler came to power after Grigory Orlov overthrew her husband Peter III. She had many lovers, including Grigory Potemkin. For 10 points, name this female tsar of Russia.", "answer": "<b><u>Catherine the</u> <u>Great</u></b> [or <b><u>Catherine II</u></b> of Russia; or <b><u>Sophie Friederike Auguste</u> </b>von Anhalt-Zerbst-Dornburg]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This state was home to the deadliest hard-rock mining disaster in American history, at</em> <em>Speculator Mine.</em> A city in this state consolidated with its surrounding Silver Bow County in 1977.This city\u2019s capital was built around the discovery of gold at Last Chance Gulch. A toxic former open-pit mine in this state, the Berkeley Pit, was excavated by Anaconda Mining. For 10 points, what state is home to the copper mining town of Butte, and has its capital at Helena?", "answer": "<b><u>Montana</u> </b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This man was the son of Rattle Blanket Woman and Worm, and he held a long grudge after</em> <em>his failed courting of Black Buffalo Woman</em>. This man served as a decoy soldier during the Fetterman Fight, and he led his forces to victory over General George Crook at the Battle of the Rosebud. He died after being stabbed at Fort Robinson. For 10 points, name this Sioux warrior who is the subject of an unfinished mountain monument in South Dakota.", "answer": "<b><u>Crazy Horse</u></b> [or <b><u>Ta-sunko-witko</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em><b><u>1,000 sandwiches were ordered for this group by the owner of the Hope Diamond, Evelyn</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Mclean.</u></b></em><b><u> The leader of this group tried to restructure it into the fascist \"Khaki Shirts.\" This</u></b> <b><u>group of Americans was visited and supported by General (+)</u>Smedley Butler. Under its leader, Walter Waters, this group established a tent city on the Anacostia Flats, from which it was (*)</b> evicted using bayonets and tear gas by Douglas MacArthur's troops. For 10 points, name this group of World War I veterans which marched on D.C. to demand payment.", "answer": "<b><u>Bonus Army</u></b> [or <b><u>B</u></b>onus <b><u>E</u></b>xpeditionary <b><u>F</u></b>orce]  {I}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>A curaca named Mateo Pumacahua aided this cause.</u></b></em><b><u> A naval fleet in service of this cause</u></b> <b><u>occupied the town of Pisco after landing in Paracas partly under the command of</u></b> <b><u>discharged British naval officer Thomas Cochrane. The Tacna uprising fought for this</u></b> <b><u>cause, which opposed Jos\u00e9 de la Serna in his role as (+)</u>Viceroy. Three years after this cause formally succeeded, the 1824 Battle of Ayacucho secured victory for this cause in an (*)</b> \"Upper\" region that later became Bolivia. For 10 points, name this cause whose success was formally declared by Jos\u00e9 de San Mart\u00edn in the new national capital of Lima.", "answer": "<b><u>Peru</u></b>vian <b><u>independence</u></b> [prompt on answers such as <b><u>South America</u></b>n <b><u>independence</u></b> which do not specify Peru; do not accept \"Bolivian independence\"]  {I}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Gillian Frank has suggested that this event was fueled by its participants\u2019 homophobia</u></b></em><b><u>.</u></b> <b><u>This event was the brainchild of a person who led The Insane Coho Lips. Its creator</u></b> <b><u>dressed up in army fatigues and was accompanied by the model Lorelei, and its</u></b> <b><u>participants were charged 98 cents admission if they</u> (+)brought along a certain item. This event was led by DJ Steve Dahl, and after its participants started rioting in Comiskey Park, the White Sox were forced to forfeit the second game of their doubleheader. (*)</b> For 10 points, in what ill-fated promotion did people bring Donna Summer and Bee Gees records to be blown up?", "answer": "<b><u>Disco Demolition Night</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "CW"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>The Army Signal Corps provided an emergency sound system for this event after the first</u></b></em> <em><b><u>one was sabotaged.</u></b></em><b><u> Strom Thurmond attempted to discredit this event by calling one of its</u></b> <b><u>organizers \"a communist, a draft dodger, and a (+)</u>homosexual.\" An explosive speech by John Lewisintended for this event was softened by this event\u2019s orchestrators Asa Philip Randolph and Bayard (*)</b> Rustin. A speech delivered at this location ended with the words, \"Thank God Almighty, we are free at last!\" and asked \"from every mountainside, let freedom ring.\" For 10 points, name this 1963 event that saw the \"I have a Dream\" speech.", "answer": "1963 <b><u>March on Washington</u></b> for Jobs and Freedom  {I}", "metadata": "VP"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Ambrose Rookwood\u2019s servants were investigated in this event while its perpetrators raided</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Warwick castle.</u></b></em><b><u> Thomas Wintour helped plan this event, which Henry Garnet was executed</u></b> <b><u>in connection with. It ended with the siege of (+)</u>Holbeche House and was discovered when Lord Monteagle gave a letter he had received to Robert (*)</b> Cecil. Robert Catesby led the planners of this event, which was thwarted when Guy Fawkes was caught. For 10 points, name this plot which sought to blow up the House of Lords and James I.", "answer": "<b><u>Gunpowder</u></b> plot [accept synonyms for plot]  {I}", "metadata": "JZ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>The USS Iwo Jima</u></b><b><u>cleared out landmines from this body of water</u></b></em><b><u>. Canadian Prime</u></b> <b><u>Minister Lester Pearson was given a (+)</u> Nobel Peace Prize for mediating a conflict over this waterway. Operation Musketeer targeted Port Said (</b>pr. sigh-EED)<b>, a city at this waterway's entrance. The fifteen-ship Yellow Fleet was trapped in this waterway as a result of the (*)</b> Six-Day War. Gamal Abdel Nasser nationalized this waterway, leading to a 1956 crisis also known as the Tripartite Aggression. For 10 points, name this Egyptian canal that shortened shipping routes between Europe and Asia.", "answer": "<b><u>Suez</u></b> Canal  {I}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This leader met with Barack Obama at the Sunnylands estate during the \"shirtsleeves</u></b></em> <em><b><u>summit.\"</u></b></em><b><u> Before taking office, this man led the 6521 Project, which cracked down on</u></b> <b><u>protesting during politically significant dates. This man's commitment to investigating both</u></b> <b><u>\"tigers (+)</u>and flies\" has led to the indictment of over seventy high-ranking officials, including former (*)</b> Politburo Standing Committee member Zhou Yongkang. This man was the Vice President under his predecessor, Hu Jintao. For 10 points, name this current President of China.", "answer": "<b><u>Xi</u></b> Jinping  {I}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Liberty poles were erected in support of this event, which saw a robbing of the mail</u></b></em><b><u>. Both of</u></b> <b><u>the two people convicted for this event, one of whom was a simpleton, were pardoned.</u></b> <b><u>David Bradford led this event, which met at (+)</u>Braddock\u2019s Field. Albert Gallatin was unable to moderate this event, which Robert Mifflin refused to (*)</b> suppress. Alexander Hamilton rode out to disperse this event with \u201cLight Horse\u201d Harry Lee\u2019s Watermelon Army. For 10 points, name this rebellion in western Pennsylvania during Washington\u2019s Presidency over a tax on a namesake beverage.", "answer": "<b><u>Whiskey</u></b> Rebellion  {I}", "metadata": "JZ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>In 1971, this man appeared on Dutch TV with Michel Foucault to do a video-recorded</u></b></em> <em><b><u>debate on \"Human Nature\".</u> </b></em><b><u>This man's Pisa lectures presented his work on \"government</u></b> <b><u>and binding theory,\" which has nothing to do with politics. With Edward Herman, this</u></b> <b><u>man published a 1988 book about mass media called (+)</u></b><em><b>Manufacturing Consent</b></em><b>, a decade after remarks downplaying the severity of mass murders in Cambodia. In his main field of study, he noted that the (*) </b>meaningless sentence \"Colorless green ideas sleep furiously\" is grammatically coherent. For 10 points, name this academic with outspoken far-left political views, an MIT linguist.", "answer": "Avram Noam <b><u>Chomsky</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>After introducing his most famous accomplishment, this man exiled himself for 10 years to</u></b></em> <em><b><u>avoid taking power as a tyrant.</u></b></em><b><u> This man who was not Themistocles</u> </b><u>(pr. them-ISS-toe-cleez)</u> <b><u>empowered his troops to capture Salamis from Megara after reciting one of his poems in</u></b> <b><u>public. This man's policy of</u> </b><em><b><u>seisachtheia</u></b></em><b><u>, (</u></b><u>pr. say-ISS-ock-TAY-uh)</u><b><u> or \u201cshaking off of</u> (+) burdens,\u201d abolished debt slavery. He created a production-based class system dominated by the \u201cfive-hundred (*)</b> bushel men\u201d and reformed many of the harsh laws of Draco. For 10 points, name this 6th century Athenian statesman and reformer.", "answer": "<b><u>Solon</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "CKM"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Villagers and British soldiers fought over some pigeons in this territory during the</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Denshawai Incident.</u></b></em><b><u> During the \u201cVeiled Protectorate\u201d, real power in this territory was held</u></b> <b><u>by Lord Cromer. The Urabi rebellion led this territory to be occupied by Great Britain in</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> 1882. A major public works project in this territory was finished by Ferdinand de Lesseps. Puppet leaders called (*)</b> Khedives ruled this territory, which was modernized by a rogue Ottoman governor who founded an independent dynasty here named Muhammad Ali. For 10 points, name this North African nation east of Libya.", "answer": "<b><u>Egypt</u></b> [or <b><u>Misr</u></b> or <b><u>Masr</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "BA"}], "bonuses": []}